<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon occasioned by the sudden death of the Reverend Mr. Nathanael Vincent, late minister of the gospel in Southwark by Nathanael Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Nathanael, d. 1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12068987</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12068987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53463</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53463)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 582:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon occasioned by the sudden death of the Reverend Mr. Nathanael Vincent, late minister of the gospel in Southwark by Nathanael Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Nathanael, d. 1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ..., and Thomas Cockeril ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53463:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon, Occaſioned by the <hi>Sudden Death</hi> Of the Reverend Mr. Nathanael Vincent, LATE Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL TAYLOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Cockeril</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noster Row.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53463:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53463:2"/>
            <head>To that part of the Church of Chriſt in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>NATHANAEL VINCENT</hi> was Paſtor.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in our Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIs commonly and juſtly eſteemed an Inſtance of the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, that the Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel is committed to thoſe who are of the ſame Make and Frame with the People to whom they Preach. But that which is a Happineſs in one reſpect, is a diſadvantage in another, <hi>viz.</hi> That tho' they are never ſo Eminent and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful, they muſt <hi>Dye</hi> as well as their Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: As it was in the Mount of old, tho' <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with his Diſciples, (and will do ſo even to the end of the World) yet <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> tho' <hi>Excellent Prophets,</hi> and <hi>glorious Creatures,</hi> must withdraw, and ſometimes <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh in a Moment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this you have a ſad inſtance in the ſurprizing Death of your beloved <hi>Paſtor,</hi> which was the Occaſion of the following Sermon, the Deſign whereof is to <hi>quiet</hi> your Minds under, and quicken you to <hi>improve</hi> ſo awakening a Providence by a diligent Preparation for your own Deceaſe.</p>
            <p>I am the rather encouraged to expect, that <hi>this,</hi> which is the <hi>main Scope</hi> of it, will be complyed withall, becauſe <hi>many</hi> of you did immediately and readily in <hi>ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> follow the advice which I gave you, (and which you may here find) in the Cloſe thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53463:3"/>
            <p>Your ſo doing gives me great hopes, that you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean your ſelves <hi>as you ought,</hi> towards a <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> when he ſhall he ſettled among you; as you <hi>have done</hi> towards him who is removed from you. I have often heard him ſpeak with great pleaſure, of the <hi>many Teſtimonies</hi> you have given, of a <hi>more than ordinary affection</hi> to him. Indeed it would have been <hi>ſtrange,</hi> if it had been otherwiſe, becauſe he could uſe the Apostle's endearing Argument with a great many of you,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Though you have ten thouſand Inſtructors in Chriſt, yet you have not many Fathers; for in Chriſt Jeſus I have begotten you through the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>great Proof and Tryal</hi> of you will be, when another who hath not that <hi>additional Advantage,</hi> ſhall enter into his Labours, and build upon that Foundation which this <hi>Wiſe Maſter-Builder</hi> hath laid, and ſo ſucceſsfully carried on among you.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to put you in remembrance, tho' you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but know it already,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7, 13.</note> that you are not to <hi>govern,</hi> but to be <hi>Ruled,</hi> as well as <hi>Taught</hi> by him; not to <hi>Trample</hi> on him, but to <hi>Submit your ſelves</hi> to him; not lightly to <hi>eſteem</hi> him, but ſhew him <hi>double Honour</hi> in <hi>Love</hi> for his <hi>Works</hi> ſake, and out of reſpect to him whom he ſhall <hi>Repreſent.</hi> For a <hi>Faithful, Ordained Miniſter,</hi> is not the <hi>People's Creature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20. Eph. 4.11.</note> but an <hi>Embaſſadour of Chriſt; his Gift</hi> from Heaven to the Church, and a <hi>Great Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> to thoſe over whom he doth <hi>Preſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the God of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> would direct you to <hi>pitch</hi> upon ſuch a One, and <hi>Treat him as ſuch,</hi> with one <hi>Common Conſent;</hi> and by proſpering his Labours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, build you up in Faith, Holineſs and Comfort to Eternal Life, is and ſhall be the Earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant for Jeſus ſake, <hi>Nathanael Taylor.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:53463:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LUKE XII. 40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Be ye therefore ready alſo: For the Son of Man cometh at an Hour when ye think not.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUr Bleſſed Saviour having Preached an Excellent Sermon, full of very Serious Advice, in many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, of which you have an Account in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Verſes of this Chapter; for the better Faſtening of the whole upon his Hearers, he falls in the Cloſe of it, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Subject of a very Affecting and Moving Nature, namely, the approaching Day of <hi>Judgment,</hi> and the Neceſſity of liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Continual Expectation of, and making daily Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for it. This he enters upon in the 35th. Verſe of the Chapter, and proſecutes to this 40th. Verſe, which I have now read unto you, wherein you have theſe four Things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Duty that he preſſes upon his Hearers, <hi>Be ye ready.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Strong Motive to back and enforce it: <hi>For the Son of Man cometh at an Hour when ye think not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Son of Man cometh:</hi> 'Tis that more Eminent and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Coming of Chriſt, to judge the World at the laſt Day, which is here plainly meant. But under this, is comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo the Day of a Man's <hi>Death;</hi> For ſo you ſhall ſine the
<pb facs="tcp:53463:4"/>Scripture uſes this Expreſſion, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.10. <hi>That you may be ſincere, and without Offence till the Day of Chriſt:</hi> 1 Tim. 6.14. <hi>Keep this Commandment till the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Theſe <hi>Phillipans</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> have been dead many Ages ſince, and yet the Day of Chriſt is not come, he hath not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared: How therefore is this to be underſtood? 'Tis meant of the Day of their <hi>Death;</hi> and ſo the Scripture words it, becauſe the Day of every particular Man's Death, and the Day of the Univerſal Judgment, is to him in Effect one and the ſame; his <hi>State</hi> is as truly, and as fully determined there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as it will be when Chriſt ſhall come to judge the World; no Alteration can poſſibly be made in it after we are once dead: As to <hi>that,</hi> ſuch as we are when we leave this World, ſuch ſhall we be when we come to ſtand before the Bar of Chriſt at the laſt Day, to receive our Unchangeable Sentence.</p>
            <p>And as this Coming of Chriſt is <hi>Certain,</hi> ſo many times 'tis a very <hi>ſudden</hi> thing too; <hi>The Son of Man cometh,</hi> that is, Death and Judgment come in <hi>an hour when you think not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Perſons here ſpoken to: Who they are, you may learn from <hi>Peter</hi>'s Queſtion, in the Verſe immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Text;
<note place="margin">v. 41.</note> wherein, ſays he, <hi>Lord, ſpeakeſt thou this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to us,
<note place="margin">v. 42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> or even to all?</hi> And from our Lord's Anſwer, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he continues this Diſcourſe of his, and particularly applies it to the <hi>Wiſe and Faithful Rulers and Stewards</hi> in his Houſe. So that the beſt of his <hi>Miniſters</hi> are as much concerned in it, as any of the Family; they are as liable to a <hi>Sudden Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> by Death and Judgment, as any of their Hearers; and 'tis as much their Intereſt, yea more, becauſe of the heavier Account they have to make, to be <hi>Always ready</hi> for it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Connexion of theſe Words with the Fore-going Verſe, Be ye <hi>therefore</hi> ready <hi>alſo.</hi> Which ſuggeſts another Motive to our Thoughts. In the preceding Verſe our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had repreſented the Suddenneſs of his coming, by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of a <hi>Thief,</hi> who ſets upon a Houſe unexpectedly in the Night, which if the Owner thereof had known of, he would certainly have watched, and not have ſuffered it to have been broken open. And then comes in my Text, <hi>Be ye therefore ready alſo:</hi> q.d. If Men are ſo prudent and careful, that they be not ſurprized in Matters of a lower Nature, where the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that they can loſe is their Worldly Subſtance, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53463:4"/>their Temporal Lives; how much more ſhould they be ſo in a matter of the higheſt Concern, whereupon their Souls, their Everlaſting Welfare, their <hi>All</hi> does depend? <hi>And therefore be ye ready</hi> in <hi>this caſe</hi> alſo; <hi>for the Son of Man cometh in an hour when ye think not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the Words thus divided and opened, I ſhall raiſe this Doctrine, as the Subject of my preſent Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>Seeing Death and Judgment may ſuddenly and unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſeize upon any, even the beſt of Men and Miniſters, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Man ſhould be always ready for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the managing this Point, I ſhall do theſe four Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſay ſomewhat to <hi>Vindicate and Juſtifie the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, in the ſudden and unexpected Death of Good Men and Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Shew you <hi>wherein this Readineſs for Death and Judgment</hi> doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Set before you <hi>the force of the Argument, from the Suddenneſs of them, to be always ready.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Apply</hi> the whole.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall ſay ſomewhat <hi>to Vindicate and juſtifie the Providence of God, in the ſudden and unexpected Death of good Men and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi> And this is requiſite, becauſe ſuch thoughts as theſe, upon ſuch Occaſions, are apt to ariſe in our Minds. <q>For a <hi>Vile</hi> Perſon indeed to be <hi>Driven away</hi> in his Wickedneſs, like Chaff and Smoak before the Wind, in thoſe Storms which his own Sins have raiſed, may be eaſily accounted for; but that very <hi>Holy</hi> Men, in the height of their Uſefulneſs, and in the midſt of their Work, ſhould be ſnatcht away almoſt in the ſame manner, ſeems at firſt View to be very ſtrange and ſevere. Their <hi>Enemies</hi> will be apt to cenſure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them, and look upon this as a <hi>Black Mark</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon them; and their <hi>Friends</hi> cannot but bitterly bewail it. For had Death made its Regular and Leiſurely advances, they might have had many an Opportunity of ſpeaking in Commendation of the Ways of God and Religion, from their own Experience, and of giving ſuitable Advice and Counſel to us; and the <hi>laſt Words</hi> of our dying Husband or Father,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53463:5"/>of our <hi>dying</hi> Friend or Paſtor, would to be ſure have made very deep and laſting Impreſſions upon us, and have been of mighty Uſe and Service to us all our Days. Why therefore, O why, did God deal ſo unkindly with him and us, as to <hi>hurry</hi> him away from us in ſo <hi>haſty</hi> a manner, as hardly to ſuffer him to ſpeak one Word, when he took his Everlaſting Fare-well of us?</q>
            </p>
            <p>By way of Reply to all this, I have theſe five or ſix Things to offer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider <hi>the Abſolute Soveraignty and Dominion of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Divine Attribute is diſplayed when he cloſeth his <hi>right-Hand</hi> to hide theſe <hi>Stars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.1.</note> wherein they were formerly <hi>held;</hi> or when he <hi>ſeals them up</hi> in a Sudden and ſo thick a Darkneſs,
<note place="margin">Job 9.7.</note> that we can neither ſee them, nor receive any further Influences from them. And if we had nothing elſe to urge in the Caſe, even this alone were enough to ſtop all our Mouths. Shall we not allow God that which we challenge to our ſelves, to <hi>Do with his own what he pleaſeth?
<note place="margin">Pſ. 46.10.</note> Be ſtill, and know that I am God.</hi> And the Exerciſe of this Attribute about <hi>Good</hi> Men, even when it ſeems to bear a little <hi>hard</hi> upon them, ſhould leaſt of all be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gretted by us; becauſe it has been employed about them in vaſtly greater Inſtances, ſo much for their Advantage. For it was Divine <hi>Soveraignty</hi> that ſelected them out of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Maſs of Mankind, when others were paſſed by, and Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with all thoſe Gifts and Graces wherein they did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. Now if the ſame Hand that framed them into Veſſels of Honour, break them in pieces <hi>with one ſingle ſtroak,</hi> it becomes us to bow our Heads, and humbly adore him, crying out, <hi>How unſearchable are his Judgments,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33. Eph. 1.11.</note> and his Ways paſt our finding out,</hi> who yet <hi>Worketh all things according to the Counſel of his own Will!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. God orders it thus, <hi>That Men may not judge of his Love or Hatred by meer external Providences.</hi> This is a deceitful Beam, at which we are very prone to weigh Men and Things; but hereby God gives us a plain and ſenſible Proof of the Truth of that Scripture,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.2.</note> that <hi>All things come alike to all, and there is one Event to the righteous and to the wicked.</hi> The beſt Rule whereby to form our Judgments as to this point, is from the <hi>manner of Men's Lives,</hi> and not from that of their <hi>Death:</hi> And that the <hi>ſuddenneſs</hi> of their Departure <hi>alone,</hi> is <hi>no Black Mark</hi> from Heaven
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53463:5"/>againſt them, is very plain, from this convincing Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there ſhall be Saints alive at that very hour wherein Chriſt ſhall appear to judge the World,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.17. 1 Cor. 15.52.</note> who ſhall be ſuddenly <hi>Changed,</hi> and <hi>Caught up in the Air, to meet him in a moment, in the twinkling of an Eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God orders it thus, <hi>Becauſe he would prevent the Prayers of his People, for the prolonging ſuch a Man's Life when his Day is come.</hi> Such a Value has God for his People, and their Prayers, that he would not have them wreſtle with him, for what he intends not to grant; and therefore when Wrath is determined againſt any, and there is no Remedy, he is wont in a great meaſure to reſtrain the Spirit of Prayer, and take off the Hearts of his People from interceding for them. But it neither is, nor can, nor ought to be ſo with them, when the Life of an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful, Chriſtian or Miniſter</hi> is in apparent danger; ſuch a one is always very Dear and Precious to them; they would,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.15.</note> as the <hi>Galatians</hi> for <hi>Paul, Pluck out their very Eyes for him;</hi> much more will they pour out their Souls to God in his Behalf: The Church would do by him,
<note place="margin">Act. 12.5.</note> if <hi>the Lord's Priſoner</hi> by a lingering Sickneſs, as they did by <hi>Peter</hi> when he was <hi>Herod</hi>'s, <hi>Prayer was made to God for him without ceaſing.</hi> Now when ſuch a Man's Work is done, and his determined Time run out, God ſuddenly removes him, that he may not give leiſure to the People to lay hold on his Arm, and endeavour to prevent that Blow, which he is reſolved to give.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God does this <hi>as an Act of Favour and Kindneſs to the Good Man himſelf.</hi> Hereby he is effectually preſerved from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe Evils, wherewith ſome of the Saints of God, who have more <hi>ſlowly</hi> gone off from the Stage of this World, have been ſorely diſtreſſed. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Great Pains and Anguiſh of a long and tedious Sickneſs:</hi> This darkens the Mind, ſhatters the Judgment, breaks the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſtakes and binds down the Soul to a Continual, ſad Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on the Miſery it feels, making a Man pine away in the bitterneſs of his Soul from Morning unto the Evening.</p>
            <p>It indiſpoſes a Man for any Duty, even that of a Delightful Communion with God in Private; hinders his Activity in it, and quickly diverts him from it. Alaſs, they are but a few <hi>Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> only that we can then preſent our God withal; a few,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53463:6"/>ſhort, broken Petitions, that we can offer up to him, and thoſe alſo with much adoe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art up a Prayer to Heaven one Minute, and fetch a <hi>longer Groan</hi> the next. The Senſe of our preſſing Evils will be like a Clog or a Weight, to hinder the flight of our Souls towards Heaven, check them when they are mounting, and preſently pull them down again. When God from <hi>Morning even to Night</hi> is <hi>breaking his Bones like a Lion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.13, 14.</note> even <hi>Hezekiah</hi> himſelf can but <hi>Chatter like a Crane, or a Swallow, or mourn like a Dove; O Lord, I am oppreſſed, undertake for me?</hi> When the Inſtrument, the Body, is thus out of Tune, and its Strings ſlackned or broken, the moſt Skilful Artiſt can't make that Melody before the Lord, as at other times he doth.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this is a ſtrong Temptation to Impatience, to Jealouſſes, to hard and ſuſpicious Thoughts of God. When he thus ſmites us, the beſt of us betray too much of Oppoſition to his good Will, and too ſtrong an Affection to our own Eaſe.</p>
            <p>Further, ſharp and long Bodily Pains, often prove the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, even to Good Men, of groat inward Trouble and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes of Soul. <hi>David</hi>'s Sickneſs often caſt him into great Doubts and Fears about his Sins, that God had not for given them. Indeed all his Griefs ſpringing from other cauſes, at laſt did run into this Channel, as any Diſtemper turns to the Plague in the Time of a Raging Peſtilence. <hi>The troubles of my Heart</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are enlarged,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 25.17, 18.</note> I am deſolate and afflicted.</hi> But what was the Reaſon of this? he lay under Affliction and Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us'd many deſponding Thoughts about the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of his Sins.</p>
            <p>A ſudden Diſpatch to a Prepared Soul is a Favour more Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, than to be continued a long while upon ſuch a Rack.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſineſs of taking a Solemn and Formal Eare well of Near and Dear Relations and Friends;</hi> which is very unpleaſant at all times, but more eſpecially in ſome caſes.</p>
            <p>As for Inſtance, When a Good Man conſiders the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the <hi>Siorms</hi> wherein he ſhall leave them. This was the Goſe of Holy <hi>David.</hi> Though he had the Covenant of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> choice and rich: <hi>Cordial</hi> at his Heart, for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his Fainting and Sinking Spirits; yet methinks I ſee how the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtood in the good Man's Eyes, at the Thoughts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53463:6"/>of thoſe Calamities which he foreſaw were coming upon his Children, after his approaching Deceaſe. And this is very plain from the Beginning and Ending of that Verſe, in the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Although my Houſe be not ſo with God, yet hath he made with me an Everlaſting Covenant, ordered in all things, and ſure; for this is all my Deſire, and all my Salvation, although he onake it not to grow.</hi> He <hi>begins</hi> the Verſe with theſe Words, <hi>Although my Non ſo be not ſo with God,</hi> that is, not <hi>as the light of the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whon the Sun riſeth, even a morning without Clouds,</hi> as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it in the beginning of the foregoing. Verſe; but many a ſad Providence will overſhadow it, and darken the Glory of it. And then he <hi>ends</hi> the Verſe with theſe Words, <hi>Although he make it not to grow,</hi> that is, not to Spring as <hi>the tender Graſs out of the Earth, by clear ſhining after the Rain;</hi> as he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it in the latter End of that 4th. Verſe; but my Family will wither away, like the Graſs of the Field, when burnt up by the Heat of the Sun. Hereby he evidently ſhows, that the Diſtreſſes that were coming upon his Family made a deep Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon him, cut him to the quick, and created ſome very uneaſie thoughts in his Mind, as he lay a Dying.</p>
            <p>Another Occaſion, wherein this taking our ſolemn Farewell is ſo very uneaſſe a thing, is, when our Friends cannot reſign us up without the Indecent Workings of a <hi>Violent and Paſſionate Sorrow:</hi> A thing that <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf could not bear, to whom the Weeping of his Friends was more grievous than any Death that he could endure from the Hands of his moſt Eura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Enemies: And therefore he that was <hi>Ready not to be bound only, but alſo to dye at Jeruſalem for the Name of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> crys out, <hi>What mean ye to weep, and to break my heart:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 21.13.</note> As tho' he could bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter endure the ſhedding of his own Blood, than the pouring out of their Tears.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Sore Buffetings of Satan.</hi> He is very buſie about the Death-Beds of good Men, and more eſpecially may we ſuppoſe him ready at ſuch a time to fall with a greater Degree of Fury and Malice, upon an <hi>Eminent Miniſter;</hi> whoſe Buſineſs it has been all his Life long to batter and deſtroy his Kingdom. When ſuch a one retreats <hi>ſlowly</hi> out of the Field, the Enemy hath the Fairer Opportunity, and being animated with Revenge, will be ſure to ſummon up all his force, and draw his Bow with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53463:7"/>his full ſtrength, to ſhoot his moſt envenomed Arrows againſt him. 'Tis a Mercy to be carried away into that Heaven, into which he can never enter, in ſo <hi>ſwift</hi> a manner, that he ſhall not be able to fling one of his fiery Darts after us, to wound, or ſo much as to affright us in our Paſſage thither.</p>
            <p>For my own part, on mature Deliberation, I don't think it a deſirable thing for a good Man, who is <hi>ready,</hi> to be worn away like a Stone, by a <hi>long and continual Dropping.</hi> May my Houſe and Soul be in order, and then the ſooner it quits this Vile Body, and leaves this wretched World, if in the twinkling of an Eye, ſo much the better. To which there is but one Circumſtance more, which I ſhould deſire may be added, <hi>viz.</hi> that I may dye <hi>Preaching the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel,</hi> or <hi>Adminiſtring the Lord's Supper.</hi> May my Taper be blown out <hi>in the Sanctuary,</hi> and may I preſently paſs in an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from Serving the Church Militant here on Earth, to joyn with the Church Triumphant in Heaven. But we muſt not be our own Chooſers; and to be ſure God will diſpoſe all things in the beſt manner for them that are his.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God orders this, <hi>as a Puniſhment to ſurviving Friends and Relations.</hi> When he ſends long Sickneſs, he weans our Hearts from them by degrees, gives us time and leiſure to get our Souls into a readineſs for parting with one another, (though even then too it is hard work for the moſt of us.) This is like digging about the Roots of a Tree, looſning and preparing of it for a more eaſie fall: But a very Sudden-Death, is like the violent blowing of it down with a Whirlwind, which tears up the ground along with it, and makes a gap ſo wide, that it is not eaſily filled up again.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> God does this for the <hi>Inſtruction of others.</hi> We think, that if a Holy Man had but time and leiſure given him, his <hi>dying</hi> Words would have a great <hi>influence</hi> upon us: And I grant there is <hi>ſomewhat</hi> in it; and they muſt needs have very impenetrable Souls, that ſhould not be at all affected with his <hi>laſt</hi> Speeches. But when God <hi>haſtily</hi> ſnatches away a good Man, Providence it ſelf turns Preacher, and crys with a <hi>loud Voice,</hi> and the <hi>Man of Wiſdom will hear, and learn;</hi> and he who does not do ſo, would not be made better, not only though the Preacher had taught him with his <hi>dying</hi> Breath, but tho'
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53463:7"/>he ſhould <hi>riſe again from the Dead</hi> to warn him. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is an awakening Conſideration to us, to uſe great <hi>Diligence in doing good to, and receiving good from our Friends and Relations, while their Lives and ours do laſt.</hi> With what Care and Diligence ſhould Parents and Miniſters inſtruct their Children, and their Flock, Watch over them, Warn, Reprove, Exhort, Beſeech, Counſel and Comfort them, Travel in Birth with them, 'till Chriſt be formed in their Hearts; endeavour to bring them into, keep and quicken them in the ways of God, and prepare them for Heaven, as not knowing how ſoon Death, that <hi>great Silencer of Miniſters,</hi> whom none can reſiſt, may ſo effectually ſtop their Mouths as not to ſuffer them to Preach their <hi>Farewell Sermon,</hi> or utter one ſingle Sentence for the good of thoſe whom they leave behind them.</p>
            <p>With what readineſs and thankfulneſs ſhould Children and People liſten to their Inſtructions, receive their Reproofs, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to their Wannings, ſhew them that Honour that is due to them for their Works ſake; not only <hi>rejoycing,</hi> but <hi>walking in the light,</hi> while they enjoy it, as not knowing how ſoon either one, or the other, or both, may be in the Grave,
<note place="margin">Job. 3.18.</note> where <hi>the Voice of the Preacher</hi> is not heard, no more than that of <hi>the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor.</hi> It is but a Melancholly thing,
<note place="margin">Luk. 17.22.</note> to have that Scripture ſullfilled upon us, <hi>The day is coming, when you ſhall deſire to ſee one of the Days of the Son of Man, and ſhall not ſee it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a loud <hi>Call to Repentance, for our Non-improvement of thoſe Advantages we enjoyed whilſt ſuch Relations were continued to us.</hi> Such is our Folly, that we ſeldom duly value, or rightly uſe any Mercy while we poſſeſs it, which gives but too much cauſe for deep Remorſe of Spirit when we are deprived of it. 'Tis true indeed, no Man can weep his Father, his Friend, his Paſtor out of the Grave. Our Loudeſt Cries will not awaken them that are fallen aſleep in Jeſus; nor can our Sighs infuſe a new Breath into them, whoſe Spirits are departed. But what cannot profit them may be of great Advantage to our ſelves: And ſo it will be if our Grief run in the right Channel; if our unſuitable Carriage towards them be deeply laid to heart, as it ought to be, when our Sins have been the Occaſion of cutting down the Spr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ding Tree, becauſe we ſat idly under its Shadow, and did not ſtretch our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53463:8"/>our hands, to gather the good Fruit wherewith it was loaden.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis a proper Means to <hi>Cure our inordinate Affection to, and Dependance upon ſurviving Friends, and all Wordly Comforts. Ceaſe ye from Man,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.22.</note> whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils,</hi> whence it eaſily paſſes out, or where it may be preſently ſtopt by any little matter, and therefore, <hi>Wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> Hereby we ſee, theſe Pipes may ſoon be cut off, theſe Springs be preſently dryed up; and therefore, becauſe at the utmoſt <hi>the Time is ſhort,</hi> and may be much <hi>ſhorter</hi> than we are aware,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.29, 30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>it remaineth that both they that have Wives, be as tho' they had none; and they that weep, as tho' they wept not; and they that rejoice, as tho' they rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not; and they that buy, as tho' they poſſeſſed not; and they that uſe this World, as not abuſing it, for the faſhion of this World paſſeth away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis a plain Admonition, that <hi>our Time and Life are in God's hands.</hi> Sometimes indeed they are ſaid to be in <hi>our own; I put my Life in my hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 12.3. Pſ. 119.109.</note> ſaid <hi>Jephtah; My Soul is continually in my hand,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> But then hereby is meant the <hi>great Dangers</hi> to which our Lives are perpetually expoſed; as a brittle Glaſs, which may preſently be broken by ſlipping from him that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsly holds it; or a valuable thing, that may be eaſily ſnatcht away from him that ſhews it in his open hand. But as to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 31.15. Eccleſ. 8.18.</note> ſo <hi>our times are in God's hand alone,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs or ſhortens them as he ſees fit, and <hi>no man hath Power over his own Spirit,</hi> (much leſs over that of his Brother) <hi>to retain it</hi> one moment when he calls for it.
<note place="margin">Pſ 49.7. Dan. 4.35, 36.</note> The moſt high doth <hi>what he will in the Army of Heaven, and among the Inhabitants of the Earth, and none can ſtay his Hand,</hi> as the proudeſt of Kings acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, when his <hi>Reaſon returned</hi> to him; and ſo ſnall we, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our be <hi>departed</hi> from us.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is a ſenſible Evidence of the <hi>Frailty and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty of our Lives:</hi> That the beſt of Men, in their beſt Eſtate, are but as the <hi>Flower of the Field,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 103.16.</note> which, as gawdy as it looks, if <hi>the Wind do bus paltiover it,</hi> immediately it is gone.</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>loud Call to us to <hi>Redeem our Time.</hi> What Stupidity is it to laviſh away one Day or Hour, which for ought we know
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53463:8"/>may be our laſt? and then there's no Preparation to be made for Eternity. We ſtand upon <hi>hollow</hi> ground, which may preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall in, and therefore <hi>Whatever thy hand findeth to do,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.10.</note> do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the Grave, whither thou goeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. 'Tis a mighty <hi>Check to Carnal Security, and pleaſing our ſelves with the hopes of a long Continued Happineſs in this World.</hi> This is but too natural to us all, when we are in flouriſhing Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. They that lye at <hi>Eaſe</hi> are very Subject to ſuch idle <hi>Dreams.</hi> That rich Man in the Goſpel, was not the <hi>only</hi> Perſon that ever ſaid to himſelf, <hi>Soul, thou haſt Goods laid up for many years, Eat, Drink,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19, 20.</note> and be merry.</hi> And how like a Fool did he look, <hi>When God ſaid unto him, This Night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee? David</hi> himſelf was ſo over-ſeen,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 30.6, 7.</note> that <hi>He ſaid in his proſperity he ſhould never be moved.</hi> But Providence ſoon confuted him, and <hi>his Mountain</hi> which he thought ſtood <hi>ſo ſtrong,</hi> was preſently, moved and ſhaken to that Degree, that he himſelf was ſuddenly <hi>caſt</hi> from it within a Hairs Breadth of the Grave; whereupon he immediately adds,
<note place="margin">v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit is there in my Blood, when I go down to the Pit, ſhall the Duſt praiſe thee?</hi> When others <hi>drop in this manner</hi> before our Eyes, 'tis a lively Comment on that Scripture, <hi>Go to now ye that ſay,
<note place="margin">James 4.13, 14, 15, 16.</note> to day or to morrow, we will go into ſuch a City, and continue there a year, and buy, and ſell, and get gain; whereas ye know not what ſhall be on the morrow:</hi> (Thou may'ſt travel to thy <hi>long Home</hi> before thou reach that City) <hi>For what is your Life? It is even a Vapor, that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Ye ought to ſay, If the Lord will, we ſhall live and do this or that: But now ye rejoyce in your Boaſtings,</hi> pleaſe your ſelves with ſuch vain Thoughts and Projects; <hi>All ſuch rejoycing is evil:</hi> 'Tis a ſottiſh Thing ſo to do, for you are not Lords of your own <hi>Lives,</hi> and therefore not of your own <hi>Actions;</hi> and if your Breath fail, in that moment all theſe great Thoughts of yours, ſhall periſh like a proud and ſwelling Bubble that is broken by a ſingle puff of Wind.</p>
            <p n="8">8. 'Tis a ſtrong Motive to <hi>Thankfulneſs to God, that he hath nor ſo ſurprized us it our Natural ſtate, or in the very Act of ſome Sin and Folly.</hi> A ſingle Affront puts <hi>our</hi> Thoughts and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits into a mighty Ferment, and Agitation, which makes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53463:9"/>our Wrath immediately kindle, like an heated Vapour, by its own Motion, in a ſultry Evening; and we are apt to be quick and ſevere in avenging our ſelves on our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, if it be in the Power of our hands. How eaſily could God have cut us off when we were Enemies to him; ſtruck us down dead at his Foot in an Inſtant, when the Weapons of Iniquity were in our Hands, without affording us any lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to bethink our ſelves what we had done, or whither we were going? Aſtoniſhing Patience, that he hath not long ſince torn away our guilty Souls from our Wretched Bodies, ſending one to the Grave, and plunging the other into Hell: That his Wrath hath not <hi>ſmoaked</hi> againſt us, yea, broke forth into a devouring <hi>Flame.</hi> His Forbearance is ſo much the more admirable,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note> becauſe perverſe Man takes an Occaſion from hence to Embolden himſelf in Sin. <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an Evil Work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the Heart of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them to do evil.</hi> His Power over <hi>himſelf</hi> is great as well as over us, otherwiſe his Anger had been let out like a Flood upon us, and we had been violently and haſtily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away before it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> 'Tis an evident Demonſtration of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of our <hi>being continually in a prepared Poſture for Death and Judgment.</hi> And this Naturally leads me to the</p>
            <p n="2">II. General propounded; which is, to ſhew wherein <hi>this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs for Death and Judgment does lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is twofold.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Habitual.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Actual.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The one, as to the <hi>State;</hi> the other, as to the <hi>Frame</hi> of our Souls: The one, in Order to a <hi>Safe</hi> Departure, the other in Order to a <hi>Comfortable</hi> one.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is an <hi>Habitual Readineſs</hi> for Death and Judgment; which lyes in theſe two things, Juſtification by Faith in the Blood of Chriſt, and Sanctification by the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:53463:9"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Juſtification by Faith in the blood of Chriſt.</hi> He is a miſerable Creature who has the guilt of any <hi>one</hi> Sin cleaving to his Soul, becauſe that <hi>ſingle</hi> guilt binds him over to Eternal Wrath. Who then can conceive the miſery of that man, who has upon him the guilt of <hi>all</hi> thoſe innumerable Sins which he has committed throughout the whole courſe of his life; <hi>every one</hi> of which, and much more <hi>all</hi> of them together, expoſe him to the Fury and Everlaſting Vengeance of God? Such a one is far from being fit for Death and Judgment, who muſt fall under that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning-Sentence, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> What terrour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion will the very preſence of Chriſt ſtrike into the Souls of theſe men!
<note place="margin">Gen. 45.3.</note> 
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> had concealed himſelf from his Brethren a long while; but when at laſt he made himſelf known to them, and ſaid, <hi>I am Joſeph;</hi> the thought of thoſe Injuries which they had done him, ſtruck them dumb, and they were <hi>troubled at his preſence, and could not anſwer him.</hi> When our Saviour ſhall appear, and ſay to an Unbeliever, <hi>I am Jeſus,</hi> That Jeſus, whoſe Blood thou haſt deſpiſed, whoſe Goſpel thou haſt ſlighted, whoſe Spirit thou haſt reſiſted, whoſe merciful Deſign thou haſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all thy life long, and wouldeſt not be reconciled to God through me, I am that very <hi>Jeſus:</hi> Theſe words will ſtrike and pierce him to the very heart, and cauſe him to <hi>wail,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.7.</note> and <hi>call to the rocks and mountains, ſaying, Fall on me, and hide me from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb; for the great day of his wrath is come,
<note place="margin">Rev. 6.16, 17.</note> and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sanctification by the Spirit of Chriſt.</hi> The moſt glittering Profeſſion, where there is not a work of Regeneration, will not avail in that day. The Fooliſh Virgins that had Lamps in their hands, but no Oil in their Veſſels, will find the door ſhut againſt them when the Bridegroom comes,
<note place="margin">Matth 25.10.</note> as not being <hi>ready to enter in with him. Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> If we are not true Penitents and Converts,
<note place="margin">Acts. 3.19.</note> our Sins are <hi>not blotted out,</hi> but ſhall remain in God's Book againſt us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our reſpective Names; and then it will not be a time of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing,</hi> but of ſcorching Heat, which we ſhall never be able to endure.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53463:10"/>
            <p>In a word, There is not a more miſerable Wretch out of Hell, than an unpardoned, and an unſanctified Man; who is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, and conſiders not whither he is haſting. All this man's Happineſs lies at <hi>the mercy of a Diſeaſe,</hi> of an <hi>Accident,</hi> of <hi>one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> for if <hi>this night</hi> God ſhould take away his Soul, where is he? Nay it all lies at the <hi>mercy of one wiſe and ſober thought:</hi> For did he but underſtand and conſider the true ſtate of his Soul with reference to Eternity, his Mirth would be changed into Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and all his Songs into Howlings and Lamentations, into Agonies and Horrors of Conſcience: For 'tis not more certain that he is at preſent out of Hell, than it is, that if he live and die in his preſent State, he ſhall in a few moments be in it.</p>
            <p n="2">II. There is an <hi>actual readineſs</hi> for Death and Judgment, and that lies in theſe following things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In a careful abſtinence from every wilful Sin, and a ſpeedy and deep repentance for any ſuch,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.14.</note> if we have been guilty of it. Wherefore, beloved, ſeeing ye look for ſuch things, be diligent, that you may be found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our principal care muſt be to <hi>refrain</hi> from ſuch Sins. For tho <hi>Repentance</hi> be a good thing, yet <hi>Innocence</hi> is better. Some men walk in a round, and a circle of ſinning and repenting, repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſinning again: Their hearts ſeeming to be much divided between God and their Luſts. According as Conviction on the one hand, or Corruption awaken'd by Temptation on the other hand doth work in them; they ſometimes forbear their Sins, and at other times yield to them: As the tops of Corn that waver and incline this way or that, according as the force of the Wind doth bend and carry them. Now the Hearts of theſe men riſe or fall with the change of their Condition, as the Quickſilver in a Weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs doth according as the ſurrounding Air is either bright and clear, or thick and foggy. A threatning Sickneſs doth as much alarm them, as the furious march of a powerful invading Army doth the weak and defenceleſs Inhabitants of any Country. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as the aking of one ſmall part of our Bodies cauſeth more ſenſible grief and pain, than the ſound and healthy ſtate of all the reſt doth of eaſe and pleaſure; ſo a <hi>few wilful Sins</hi> do cauſe more of terror in the Conſcience, than a great many good
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53463:10"/>Actions are able to convey of ſupport and comfort to it. And I dare appeal to the Experience of all ſober men, when they are any thing ſerious, whether theſe are not the things that do <hi>ſhake their confidence,</hi> and make them jealous of themſelves. So many wilful Sins as a man hath, of late eſpecially, been guilty of, even after he hath repented of them, ſo many Arguments hath he to make him doubt of his own Sincerity; ſo many weights there are in the other Scale, that make the Balance at leaſt to hang even, ſo that he hardly knows what to think of himſelf; and in a dying-hour his miſgiving-Heart will be apt to ſay the worſt, and reproach him that he hath not been right with God, nor ſound in his Statutes. And as <hi>all</hi> wilful ſins muſt be diligently watcht againſt, ſo</p>
            <p>In particular, <hi>Cruelty and Oppreſſion</hi> muſt be avoided.
<note place="margin">Jam. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall have judgment without mercy, that ſheweth no mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A rigid exacting thoſe Debts</hi> which our poor Brother is not able to pay.
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.33, 34.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord was wrath with that wicked ſervant that would not forgive his fellow-ſervant a few pence, and commanded him to be delivered to the tormenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and <hi>Smiting</hi> of our Brethren.
<note place="margin">Luke 12.41.</note> 
               <hi>If that ſervant ſhall ſay in his heart, My Lord delayeth his coming, and ſhall begin to beat the men-ſervants, and maidens, and to eat and drink with the drunken; the Lord of that ſervant will come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour when he is not aware.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it holds, not only as to <hi>theſe particular</hi> Sins, but as to <hi>all other</hi> wilful ones; as appears from what our Saviour adds, <hi>And that Servant that knew his Maſter's Will,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 47.</note> and prepared not himſelf, neither did according to his Will</hi> (and much more if he knowingly <hi>went againſt it</hi>) <hi>ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In great diligence and readineſs for the doing of every good work in its proper ſeaſon;</hi> every Duty reſpecting either God, or our Selves, or our Neighbour: For a Chriſtian is like a Clock or Watch that hath <hi>ſeveral diſtinct Motions;</hi> and as to every one of theſe, will the Judge examine us, when he ſhall appear. This is what our Saviour means, when he tells us,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.35.</note> our <hi>loyns</hi> ſhould be <hi>girt about,</hi> in a poſture ready for any Service that our Maſter calls us to. And <hi>bleſſed is that Servant whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.11.</note> Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved, what manner of Perſons ought ye to be in all Holy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and Godlineſs!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53463:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In the lively exerciſe of every grace, as we have occeſion for it,</hi> whether active or paſſive. Some Graces are to be exerciſed every day, be our circumſtances what they will, ſuch as Faith in Chriſt, Love to God, and the like. Others are to be exerciſed under ſome peculiar circumſtances, as the Providence of God gives us occaſion, and a call thereunto; ſuch as Patience, Submiſſion to God, Faith in his Promiſes, <hi>&amp;c. If need be, ye are in heavineſs through manifold tribulations,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7.</note> that the trial of your faith, being much more precious than that of gold which periſheth though it be tried with fire, might be ſound unto praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> That is, either that <hi>you</hi> may be praiſed, and honoured, and glorified, as having given ſuch evident proofs of the Sincerity of your Faith under very trying Providences; or elſe, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that day may be glorified, when your ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Behaviour ſhall be diſplayed in the view of all the World, as the Fruit of his Death and Grace; and men ſhall ſee what excellent perſons his Followers have ſhown themſelves to be, through his ſtrengthening of them, which will reflect an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon him, as well as upon them. The Skill of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, and the Beauty of the Veſſel will be both admired together.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>In the diligent improving of every Talent for his Service,</hi> Life; Health, Strength, Reputation, Intereſt, Power, Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are Talents which he hath committed to our Charge; and when he comes, he will ſtrictly enquire what uſe we have made of them. And we know what became of the Unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant: Thoſe <hi>Feet</hi> which carried him to the place where he buried his Lord's Money, inſtead of walking with it to the Exchangers; and thoſe <hi>Hands</hi> which were employed in conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it inſtead of trading with it, were <hi>bound;</hi> and for hiding it in the Earth, he himſelf was caſt into Hell. What then will be the caſe of him who <hi>abuſeth many</hi> of them, contrary to the intent for which they were given?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>In perſeverance in Faith and Holineſs to the laſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> For <hi>if we draw back, his Soul will have no Pleaſure in us.</hi> And how then ſhall we be able to look him in the Face? Deſerters are wont to be more ſeverely treated than thoſe who were always open and profeſſed Enemies. A ſenſe of this hath come with ſo great a <hi>weight</hi> on ſome Backſliders in Judgment and Practice, as to break their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and ſink them down into the Depths of Deſpair in the cloſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53463:11"/>of their Days. Their awaken'd Conſciences have laſht them with Whips of Steel, and with ſiery Scorpions. And therefore, <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children, abide in him, that when he ſhall appear,
<note place="margin">1 Joh 2.23.</note> we may have confidence, and not be aſhamed before him at his coming.</hi> If Chriſt when he was a <hi>Friſoner,</hi> by one Look did ſo daſh <hi>Peter</hi> out of Countenance, when in Words he diſowned him, as to make him go forth immediately and weep bitterly; what overwhelming-Sorrow and Confuſion will his Majeſtick and angry Countenance ſtrike all thoſe into, who <hi>deny him in their Works,</hi> when he ſhall appear in all the Solemnity of a Publick <hi>Judge,</hi> in the Glory of his Father, ſurrounded with all his holy Angels!</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>In a great weanedneſs from this World, and having our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſtrongly ſet upon Heavenly things.</hi> Our Saviour plainly warns us, That too deep a concern about earthly matters, expoſes men to a fatal Surprize by this great day.
<note place="margin">Luk 21.34.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be over-charged with ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs, and the cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares.</hi> How bitter are the <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and much more the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> of Death to him whoſe Affections cleave ſtrongly to this wretched World! Violence muſt be uſed to ſeparate him from it. But he who ſits looſe to all things here below, is eaſily parted from them: Like the Beams of Light, which gently touch the Earth, but not being <hi>tied</hi> to it, are eaſily withdrawn from it, as ſoon as ever the Sun begins to ſet, and the Evening to come on.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>In getting our Evidences for Heaven bright and clear.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.8.</note> Abraham</hi> indeed, at the call of God, readily departs from his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into a Foreign Land, <hi>not knowing whither he went.</hi> But 'tis impoſſible any one ſhould be willing to leave this World and paſs into the other, if he be at a great loſs in his own mind whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he is going, to Heaven or Hell, and which of theſe two muſt be his everlaſting Habitation. Where Eternal Happineſs or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is the Doubt, it muſt needs be a very uneaſy thing to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Perſon (and men are generally ſo in their laſt minutes) to be toſt up and down between Hopes and Fears. But when our Title to that bleſſed Inheritance is clear, and our Aſſurance is ſtrong, we may chearfully lay down our Bodies and reſign up our Souls. No man can live with half that Comfort and Joy as ſuch a man may dye withal.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53463:12"/>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>In watching, waiting, and expecting Death and Judgment eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day:</hi> not fancying that certainly <hi>we ſhall</hi> dye; but thinking within our ſelves, that for ought we know <hi>we may</hi> dye every day. Frequently ſeaſoning our Hearts with ſuch ſerious Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as theſe, will be like a daily watering the Tree at the roots, which makes the Sap to riſe and ſhoot up into every Branch, it will quicken us to the performance of all the forementioned particulars; and have the ſame good Influence upon us, as the expecting that Thieves may come every Night, which makes us careful to provide for our own Defence.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>In well ſettling your worldly Eſtates.</hi> Do this in the time of Health, that it may be <hi>your laſt Will; yours,</hi> and not <hi>the Will of thoſe that are about you,</hi> who otherwiſe may be practiſing upon you when you are ſick and weak in Body and Mind too. The neglecting, or the not doing this to their own full Satisfaction, has cauſed very great uneaſineſs of mind in many, when they have been ſuddenly within the near Views of Death. We need not to have theſe worldly matters to diſtract and diſcompoſe us, when we have much weightier Affairs, enough to take up all the little remainder of our Time, and our moſt ſerious Thoughts. For,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If our <hi>Heads be clear,</hi> and we have leiſure, we muſt ſeriouſly <hi>review the State of our own Souls.</hi> Otherwiſe it will be as improper for us ſo to do, as it would for a man that is to make a Map of any Country, to pretend to ſurvey it in a <hi>foggy</hi> day. In this caſe we muſt live upon, and draw Comfort from <hi>the former Trials of our ſelves. We muſt alſo renew our Repentance</hi> for all thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sins we can remember, and <hi>our Faith</hi> in the Blood of Chriſt for the pardon of them; and again <hi>commit and give up our Souls</hi> to him; recalling to our minds ſome of the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God, that are moſt ſuitable to our preſent condition; ſpeaking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, if we are able, <hi>in the behalf of God, and Chriſt, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Holineſs,</hi> that may be of uſe to thoſe that we ſhall leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us; <hi>lifting up our Hearts to the heavenly Glory, and commending our departing Spirits into the hand of God and Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>General.</hi> I come to ſhew you wherein the force of this Argument lies, from <hi>the ſuddenneſs of Death and Judgment, to be always ready for them.</hi> And,</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53463:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Death and Judgment will not ſtay beyond the appointed time, till we get ready.</hi> Thy Days are numbred, thy Glaſs has been turned up, and running for ſome time; there are, it may be, but a few Sands more, how few God only can toll; and when they are run out, ready or unready all is one, away thou muſt. Now God gives thee Time, improve it, that <hi>the long-ſuffering of God</hi> may be <hi>Salvation</hi> to thee. But if thou trifle it away now, when the Decree is gone forth to cut down the barren Tree, it ſhall not ſtand a moment longer. Many a Time haſt thou been ſick, and the conſciouſneſs of thy having made little or no Proviſion for Eternity, has made thee cry out in the bitterneſs of thy Soul, <hi>O ſpare me a little longer!</hi> God has been merciful to thee once and again; but the time is a coming, when he will be ſo no more. How many haſt thou known of thy ſinful Companions, who have cried as loudly as thou canſt do, <hi>Yet a little more time!</hi> But God would not vouchſafe it, but they have been hurried away to Judgment before they have made up their Accounts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Little or nothing is to be done to get ready upon a ſudden Surprize by Death.</hi> Thou may'ſt be ſtruck dead in a moment. Thy Diſeaſe may lye in thy Head, may ſo diſtract and cloud thy Brain, that as one well ſaith, if the meer ſaying, <hi>Lord have mercy upon me,</hi> would ſave thy Soul (as it will not) yet thou ſhalt not be able to utter ſo ſhort a Petition. But ſuppoſe thou haſt a little <hi>longer warning,</hi> how unlikely is it thou ſhouldeſt get thy Soul into a meet poſture for Death and Judgment, if then it be to begin? When thou haſt ſpent Forty or Fifty Years in Wickedneſs, is a few Hours time ſufficient to make thy Peace with God for ſuch a multitude of Provocations, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Change of thy Heart and Nature, ſo conſirmed in Sin? Soul and Body, by Phyſick and Pains are miſerably indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for ſo ſerious a matter; and there is little hopes, that the Grace of God, which thou haſt ſo long reſiſted, ſhould then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thee in a moment. It may be thy <hi>Ignorance</hi> will be ſo great, that having a clear ſight of thy manifold and crying Sins, and little or no knowledge of a Saviour, thou wilt be at thy Wits-end, not knowing what to do. It may be God's <hi>Spirit</hi> will <hi>withdraw,</hi> and leave thee to the hardneſs of thy own Heart; and then thou wilt remain ſtupid as a Block: Or elſe the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53463:13"/>Thoughts of ſo many Sins, of the Terrors of God, the near Approaches of Death and Judgment, and amazing Fears of Hell, will caſt thee into terrible Pangs and Agonies of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and overwhelm thee with a total Deſpair. Some ſuch I have known, who upon their Sick and Death-Beds have cried out, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone, eternally undone,</hi> there is <hi>no Hope, no Mercy</hi> for us; <hi>there remaineth nothing but a certain fearful looking for of Judgment and fiery Indignation from the Lord to conſume us:</hi> Who have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>howled like a Beaſt, and roared out like a damned Soul;</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I hear the <hi>doleful</hi> Sound continually in my Ears, and I hope I ſhall never totally forget it.</p>
            <p>But for the preſent, let us ſuppoſe the <hi>beſt;</hi> Provided thou ſhouldeſt prove <hi>a true Fonitent</hi> (which is very unlikely) yet, without a Divine Revelation thou wilt not be able to <hi>know</hi> it. Many have been affrighted by Sickneſs into ſeemingly very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Purpoſes, and have been taken for ſincere Converts; but when they have recovered, have returned again, like the Dog to his Vomit, and the Sow that has been waſhed to her wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the mire. It may be this has been <hi>thy own caſe,</hi> a Fit of Sickneſs made a great change in thy <hi>Countenance,</hi> but a greater in <hi>Thoughts.</hi> But with thy Health thou haſt recovered thy ancient <hi>Looks,</hi> and returned to thy <hi>Old Sins</hi> again; and all thy good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions have vaniſht away like the <hi>Viſions of the Night</hi> when a man awakes, or <hi>the Dew of the Morning</hi> when the Sun is riſen. The Pangs thou haſt undergone have not been like thoſe of a <hi>Woman in Travel,</hi> which end in the Birth of a living Child; but like the racking and tormenting Pains of the <hi>Gout or Stone,</hi> which wear off, but no good comes of them. And who can aſſure thee that ſpecial Grace hath now fixed and eſtabliſhed thy Heart, which hath ſo often ſtarted aſide like a deceitful Bow? So that thou wilt unavoidably dye in a dreadful Cloud, and paſs by the very Gates, and within a near View of the Flames of Hell, even though thou ſhouldeſt be received into Heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>It will greatly torment thee, if Sickneſs ſhould find thee unready.</hi> Oh how wilt thou befool and condemn thy ſelf, and ſay, How often was I put in mind of ſuch an Hour as this? How often have I been called upon to prepare my Soul for it? How often did I purpoſe to do it? I was even ready to yield ſometimes, but ſtill I deferred it till a more convenient Seaſon (as I called it;)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53463:13"/>ſuch a Fool was I, and ſo like a Beaſt have I carried it! Surely I had not the Underſtanding of a man within me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Great is the Happineſs of thoſe who are ready for a ſudden Death.</hi> Nothing can make them miſerable; they walk in the Light of God's Countenance, Peace of Conſcience, Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, and a daily delightful Communion with God; a thing ſo raviſhing, that as that Nobleman ſaid, when in his low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he was tempted with the offer of a Bag of Gold to return to Popery, <hi>Their Money periſh with them that would not prefer one Hours Communion with God before all the Silver and Gold in this World.</hi> They drink abundantly of that ſweet Wine, which hath a far more delicious reliſh and taſte than all the Pleaſures of this World, were the Spirits of them all extracted and mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one Draught.</p>
            <p>And as they do not <hi>live,</hi> ſo neither do they <hi>dye</hi> at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rate of other men. Much of their <hi>Maſter's Joy</hi> comes down into them, before they are received up into it; they dye ſmiling, yea go away in Triumph into that bleſſed Place where Delight and Praiſe ſhall be their everlaſting Work and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And Laſtly. <hi>The Conſequences will be very dreadful, if thou art not ready.</hi> If thou haſt not the <hi>habitual and fundamental</hi> readineſs, that is, if thou art not juſtified and ſanctified, thou art loſt for ever. And except theſe men's Conſciences are ſeared, if a Cloud be but <hi>gathering,</hi> if ſome threatning Sickneſs do but hover over them, it caſts them into a mighty Confuſion: But if it actually <hi>ſeize</hi> them, they are in the ſame condition with <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> when he ſaw the Fingers of a man's hand writing he knew not what; tho' he could not read nor underſtand the myſtical Character, yet his guilty Conſcience concluded it was a Sentence of Death and Wrath; whereupon his <hi>Thoughts troubled him,</hi> and his <hi>Knees ſmote one againſt another;</hi> and his <hi>Countenance changed white</hi> as that <hi>Wall</hi> on which the Hand-writing appeared: And <hi>he</hi> could not be more in haſte for his Wiſe-men, than <hi>they</hi> are for the Phyſician, to tell them what their Fate is like to be.</p>
            <p>And though thou haſt the Fundamental, yet if thou haſt not the <hi>actual</hi> readineſs for Death too, thou wilt be full of Fears and inward diſtreſs of Soul, dye very uncomfortably, and go away trembling into the other world.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53463:14"/>
            <p n="4">IV. And Laſtly. The <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Learn hence the <hi>Reaſon of Holy Men's ſtrictneſs in Religion.</hi> They dare not follow a multitude to do wickedly, nor aſſume to themſelves ſo great a latitude in practice as their Neighbours. They <hi>think,</hi> and therefore they <hi>walk</hi> otherwiſe than the reſt of mankind do. They take heed to their Feet, becauſe they don't know but the next ſtep they make may be into the other World. They have impreſſed upon their Minds a deep ſenſe of thoſe Words of our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Rev. 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I come as a Thief: Bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his garments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How ſad is it, that ſo few are, or take any care to get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ready?</hi> There is not a plainer inſtance of the deplorable Corruption and Folly of human Nature than this, That we ſtand in need of Divine Inſtruction by a powerful hand practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally to know this common and obvious thing, <hi>how frail</hi> we are. God had pronounced that Severe Sentence againſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> That that whole Generation ſhould die in the Wilderneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leſs than forty Years. And conſequently in ſo vaſt a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of men, who were all of them to drop in ſo ſhort a compaſs of Time, they could not chuſe but have daily Spectacles of Mortality before their Eyes; and yet <hi>Moſes</hi> was jealous that not a man among them would duly apprehend ſo plain a thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Help from Heaven; He therefore digeſts his own ſerious Thoughts on this Point into a ſolemn Prayer, for the uſe of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> that ſo he might lead the People in their <hi>Devotions;</hi> as well as in their <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Journeyings</hi> through the Wilderneſs. Yea, tho' he was ſo eminent a Saint, and ſo well skilled in <hi>all the Learning of the Egyptians,</hi> of which <hi>Arithmetick</hi> was one part; yet he ſaw a neceſſity of Divine Grace for <hi>himſelf</hi> too, that he might be able to <hi>reckon aright</hi> in this matter; which therefore he prays for in his own behalf as well as theirs, <hi>So teach us to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our days,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 90.12.</note> that we may apply our hearts to wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Folly of the generality of Mankind as to this point,
<note place="margin">Deut. 29.4</note> is ſo very manifeſt, that we have too much cauſe to take up <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Complaint, That <hi>the Lord hath not given them a heart to perceive, and eyes to ſee, and ears to hear unto this day;</hi> which is a plain argument that he hath not been ſeriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53463:14"/>unto, nor his Inſtructions obediently complied withal. Our Saviour indeed in his Parable ſuppoſes the number of the Wiſe and Prepared, the Fooliſh and Unready Virgins, to be <hi>equal,</hi> five of the one, and five of the other: But ſurely in our days there is a vaſt diſproportion between theſe two ſorts of perſons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Are you ready for Death and Judgment, yea or no?</hi> Would not an immediate Summons to appear before the Bar of Chriſt, put you into as much Diſorder and Confuſion, as a ſleepy and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Army, by the ſound of their Enemies warlike Inſtruments in the dead of the Night?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Will you make it the great buſineſs of your Lives, from this time forword, to prepare for this day;</hi> that you may not be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by it? To do this, is the Wiſdom of <hi>all:</hi> But it would be a moſt unaccountable Folly in <hi>ſome</hi> men, if it ſhould be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by them. <hi>Ex. Gr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe who have <hi>weak and crazy</hi> Bodies, and are frequently alarm'd by Sickneſs. If the Roof of the Houſe be fallen, and the Floor be rotten, and ſeveral pieces of the Wall broken down, and the ragged Remains are viſibly bowing and tottering every day, 'tis evident to our very Senſes it cannot ſtand long.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are <hi>old,</hi> whoſe <hi>grey Hairs</hi> make 'em look like Ears of Corn which are <hi>white</hi> and ripe for the Harveſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are the <hi>Watchmen</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and whoſe buſineſs it is to awaken others; how inexcuſable would they be, if they fall aſleep themſelves?
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh,</hi> (both the Brothers.) Mr. <hi>Okes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shewen</hi> of <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> Mr. <hi>R. Mayo.</hi>
               </note> Several of <hi>our Orde</hi> of late have been <hi>ſtruck in the Pulpit,</hi> and tho' they have languiſht ſome days, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recovered the fatal Blow they there received. They have been like a Taper, which while 'tis burning and ſhining in the Candleſtick, on a ſudden drops down into the Socket, where it lies for a little time, ſhooting up its wavering and trembling Light, which is immediately ſuckt back again, and extinguiſht in a few moments. That you may not be ſurprized by this laſt Enemy,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Strengthen your Faith</hi> about the coming of Chriſt, and be much in conſideration of it, and the ſuddenneſs of it too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be often <hi>putting Queſtions</hi> to your ſelves, in a very ſerious anner; Am I ready indeed? What if I ſhould dye before to morrow comes? O my Soul, art thou in ſuch a Poſture as thou art willing to be found in, when Chriſt ſhall appear.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53463:15"/>
            <p n="3">3. Shame your ſelves by conſidering <hi>what care you uſe to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and prevent a Surprize, in matters of a lower nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Reflect upon your ſelves, <hi>What Thoughts you had the laſt time you were Sick, and knew that you were unready, and were inwardly tormented in your minds at the Thoughts thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Improve the ſudden Death of others to this end.</hi> This is the Voice of that Providence, that ſo haſtily removed your late excellent Paſtor, Mr. <hi>Nathanael Vincent.</hi> I need not to tell you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>June</hi> 22.</note> How on <hi>Tueſday</hi> was ſevennight he was ſuddenly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ill in the Morning, and had leiſure only to ſay, <hi>I find I am a dying; Lord, Lord, Lord, have mercy on my Family and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> So near did you his People lye to his Heart, even in his laſt Moments. Herein he reſembled his and our common Lord, <hi>who having loved his own, loved them even to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was the Son of a Godly Miniſter, Mr. <hi>John Vincent;</hi> and a living Confutation of that Scandal, that the Children of the Prophets do more commonly than others prove Sons of <hi>Belial:</hi> As alſo was his late Brother, Mr. <hi>Thomas Vincent,</hi> a Miniſter of eminent Uſefulneſs in <hi>London</hi> while he lived, eſpecially in the time of the dreadful <hi>Plague,</hi> and whoſe Memory is ſtill deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly very dear and precious to thoſe that knew him; like a <hi>Roſe</hi> which adorns the Garden, and perfumes the Air while 'tis growing on the Tree,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's</hi> Life. Part 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. p. 95.</note> and hath a fragrant ſmell too a long time after it is <hi>gathered</hi> and <hi>dead.</hi> For he was a <hi>ſerious, humble, godly man, of ſober Principles, and great Zeal and Diligence;</hi> as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> doth truly deſcribe him.</p>
            <p>He was of ſuch pregnant Parts, and ſo ſtrong a Memory, that by the help of that, when he was but <hi>Seven years Old,</hi> he was wont, for the eaſe of his tired Father, to repeat his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the Family in the Evenings of the Lord's Day. He was admitted as a Member of the Famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> about the <hi>Eleventh</hi> Year of his Age, and went out <hi>Maſter of Arts</hi> about <hi>Eighteen;</hi> Preached publickly as a <hi>Lecturer</hi> at <hi>Pulborow</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi> before Twenty; and at the Age of <hi>One and Twenty</hi> was <hi>Ordained</hi> and fixed as Rector of <hi>Langly-Marſh</hi> in <hi>Bucking-hamſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After his <hi>Ejectment,</hi> and a few years ſpent in a private Family, he came to this City the year after the Fire, and quickly ſettled among you in this Place. And this being the moſt publick
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53463:15"/>Sphere wherein he moved, let us <hi>briefly</hi> conſider him as a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and as a Chriſtian (for I ſhall not draw him at his <hi>full length).</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As a <hi>Miniſter.</hi> He had a good ſhare of <hi>Learning,</hi> and other Miniſterial Abilities; which he was daily improving by great diligence in his Study, as wiſely conſidering, he that ſpends on the main ſtock, how large ſoever that may be, and does not endeavour to lay more in, will quickly come to Poverty.</p>
            <p>He had a great Zeal againſt <hi>bold Intruders into the Work of the Miniſtry.</hi> And I hope you that are his People will herein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble him; turn away from thoſe Men, and do not ſo much as vouchſafe them the Hearing. Theſe <hi>Vermin</hi> begin to ſwarm among us, and diſturb us by their hideous Noiſe, not in <hi>Corners</hi> or <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> but in our very <hi>Pulpits;</hi> and are like to prove an <hi>Egyptian Plague</hi> to us: If theſe Illiterate Antinomian Uſurpers are not ſpeedily and effectually diſcountenanced by Miniſters and People too, they who are already the Blemiſh of <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> will quickly prove the total <hi>Ruin</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>He had <hi>Luther</hi>'s Three Qualifications to make a Man a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Miniſter; he gave himſelf much to <hi>Meditation</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> to his laſt, that he might work things upon his own Soul, and thence more effectually convey them to yours. If Divine Truths are firſt <hi>Engraven</hi> on our Hearts, then are we moſt likely to <hi>Print</hi> them on thoſe of our Hearers. And as for <hi>Temptation,</hi> he had been ſorely exerciſed and diſtreſſed by it in his Younger days; though from that time <hi>Satan</hi> left him, and moleſted him no more in that manner.</p>
            <p>He had a <hi>natural Fervency</hi> of ſpirit, which made him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vehement in every thing that he eſpouſed; which Time and Experience did <hi>correct</hi> in ſome matters, making him more Calm and Moderate towards our <hi>Brethren</hi> who differ from us in things that lie <hi>remote enough from the Foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had a marvellous <hi>Readineſs</hi> and <hi>Quickneſs</hi> in Anſwering any difficult Queſtions, as ſoon as ever they were Propounded to him. His Notions were <hi>faſt locked</hi> up in a faithful Memory, but yet the door did preſently <hi>fly open at the firſt knock,</hi> ſo as that he could eaſily bring them forth at pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But the Gift of <hi>Breaching,</hi> that moſt eſſential and uſeful Part of a Miniſter's Work, was that peculiar Talent wherewith God had Bleſſed and Honoured him. He opened and applied the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53463:16"/>great Truths of the Goſpel, with that mixture of Plainneſs and Majeſty, with that meaſure of Life and Power, that ſhowed he had a deep ſenſe upon his own Heart of the great Ends of the Miniſtry, the Glory of God, and the Salvation of Souls. His Delivery and Carriage were Graceful; his <hi>Speech Sound,</hi> ſuch as could <hi>not be Condemned;</hi> his Sermons Warm and Serious, ſuch as commanded Attention, raiſed Affection, and ſtruck an Awe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Conſciences of thoſe who heard them. And no wonder then he had ſo general an Acceptance, and ſo eminent Succeſs. Many were the <hi>Seals</hi> of his Miniſtry; of <hi>this and that man</hi> it may be truly ſaid, That <hi>they were born here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider him <hi>as a Chriſtian.</hi> He has been noted for this, that he was very ready upon all occaſions to ſtart ſome <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>ſerious Diſcourſe;</hi> a thing that is grown almoſt out of faſhion among the Profeſſors of this Age. When we meet together, we talk of News, of worldly Affairs, it may be of the Sins and Miſcarriages of our Brethren; we can ſpend whole Hours toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and hardly drop one word, of God, or Chriſt, or Heaven, all the while. But hardly any Company could he come into, but he was like an open Box of precious Ointment, he would leave ſome ſweet Perſume, ſome Heavenly Diſcourſe behind him.</p>
            <p>His Compaſſion to the <hi>Poor</hi> was great, to whom he gave Alms, and Holy Advice at the ſame time; and was very liberal in both, doing Good at once to Body and Soul too.</p>
            <p>He was a Cloſe Walker with God, and found the fruit of it, by enjoying a conſtant, ſettled, calm Aſſurance of the Divine Love, for many years together; which paſs'd the <hi>trial,</hi> and ſtood firm and unſhaken, ſeveral times, when he verily thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be near his End. When his neareſt Relation expreſs'd her great Sorrow at the Apprehenſions of his Death, in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sickneſs, he replied, <hi>Why weep you for me, who am going to the Eternal Inheritance?</hi> And then brake forth into a large and ſerious Diſcourſe of the Joys of the Saints above.</p>
            <p>He had frequent Alarms by the Providence of God, and had a deep ſenſe of his own Mortality thereupon. He ſaid to a Friend a few days ſince, I <hi>do not expect to live long, but I bleſs God I am ready.</hi> Any one that would ſee his very Heart and Soul, let him read the Introduction to thoſe uſeful Sermons of his about
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53463:16"/>
               <hi>the benefit of Affliction,</hi> Preached and Printed on the occaſion of his having been twice ſeized with a Death-threatning Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <p>His Patience and Reſignation under Afflictions, and ſharp and ſevere pains, was very remarkable. When, upon that occaſion, a near Relation expreſſed too much of concernedneſs, as he thought, for him; His Anſwer was, <hi>Submiſſion, Submiſſion beſt becomes Creatures.</hi> And it was a frequent ſaying with him, <hi>I am in the hands of my gracious God and Father, who beſt ſees what is beſt for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Man,</hi> this was the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> this was the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> whom you have loſt. They who ſaw his Face here ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and with ſo much delight, ſhall never ſee it more in this place. They who heard the Voice of this Charming Preacher with ſo much content, ſhall never hear it more. He ſhall watch over, exhort, rebuke, guide, direct, comfort you no more. Seeing he is gone whence he ſhall not return, and can give you no more Advice; ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e to do it. And I ſhall ſpeak a few things to you as a Society, and I hope my Counſel will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be not <hi>too haſty</hi> in filling up the Breach which God has made upon you; and yet be not <hi>too dilatory</hi> neither.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Seek out a man, that comes as near as may be to your deceaſed Paſtor, in Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Miniſterial Gifts;</hi> a better Pattern I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not propound to you. And though this be no very eaſy matter, yet I do not totally deſpair but ſuch a one may in time be found out; eſpecially if the <hi>United Miniſters</hi> in and about this City, be applied unto, as I think <hi>they ought to be upon ſuch an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Till this be done, <hi>be very careful whom you admit into the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</hi> 'Tis not ſit that every <hi>private Brother</hi> ſhould aſſume the liberty of thruſting up whom he has a mind unto. Nothing ſhould be done of this nature, without the concurring conſent of thoſe who have had ſome ſhare in the <hi>managing the Affairs of this Society.</hi> And if this Rule be neglected, it opens a. wide Gap for Breaches and Diviſions, for Confuſion and every Evil work.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Let the Lord's Supper be kept up at its uſual and ſtated times.</hi> The Neighbouring Paſtors lawfully may adminiſter it to you;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53463:17"/>and I doubt not but they will at your requeſt. This will keep your Members from ſcattering, who elſe will be ready to run into other Folds, and may be tempted from an Occaſional, to ſix in a Stated Communion: And hereby no opportunity will be given to any of thoſe <hi>People,</hi> who whether by <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from others, or not, I liſt not to enquire, are turned <hi>Privateers,</hi> endeavouring to pick up any Rich Veſſel that is ſeparated from the reſt of the Fleet.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let <hi>not any of the Members of this Society, take this opportunity of leaving it.</hi> I know what the Plea of ſome will be, The <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteneſs</hi> of their Dwellings. But ſurely, though your <hi>Paſtor</hi> be, yet your <hi>Houſes</hi> I ſuppoſe are not removed, but ſtand ſtill in the ſame place they did, and are altogether as near as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were. But, whatever you may do <hi>hereafter,</hi> don't drop off now; ſtay till a Succeſſor be choſen, and the Society well fixed under him; the pulling out of one or two Pins at ſuch a time as this is, may ſhake and endanger the whole Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If there be a neceſſity, and you muſt, or will be gone; be not in haſte; <hi>wait but for one year, till things are ſetled,</hi> and then you may ſlide off without much Obſervation or Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And Laſtly, <hi>Break not into Parties and Factions:</hi> Beware of <hi>hard Speeches, unjuſt Surmiſes, ſecret Heart-burnings</hi> and <hi>Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> one of another. Beware of <hi>private Cabals,</hi> and of being <hi>practiced upon</hi> by any without Doors, who may have little and wicked Deſigns upon you, for the tearing and dividing you in pieces, and ſending a <hi>Fireſhip</hi> in among you, in order to the ſcattering of you: And ſuch there are, who, while they are at a diſtance, and by the <hi>Colours</hi> that they hang out one would take for Friends, but ſhall find them at laſt to be real Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe all with the words of the Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Remember him that had the Rule over you, that ſo often ſpake to you the word of God; whoſe Faith follow, conſidering the end of his Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And conſider his <hi>End</hi> aright, ſo that you may all fall in with ſhe Exhortation of our Saviour in my Text, To be <hi>always ready;</hi> For the <hi>Son of man</hi> may <hi>come upon</hi> you, as he did upon him, <hi>in an hour when you think not.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
